All right, בוקר טוב, Boker tov, שושן פורים שמח. Shushan Purim Sameach.
We pick up with, you know what, let's pick up from the
bottom of today's דף Daf ל"ב, Lamed bet, but let's pick up
from the bottom of ל"א, Lamed aleph, ל"ב, Lamed bet, and start
the סוגיא Sugya from the beginning here. הבא על אחותו ועל אחות
אביו. Ha-ba al achoto ve-al achot aviv. Okay, so after having a
whole discussion about the first part of the משנה, Mishna, which was,
which was where somebody who is חייב כרת, chayav kares, deserving of
כרת, kares, still will pay the קנס knas for the case of
rape and of a נערה, na'arah, of a young wo- of a-
of a young woman or a girl.
We and the issue that that's not the position of רבי נחוניא
בן הקנה Rabbi Nechunya ben Ha-kanah that says that not only is
a execution of court or a sin deserving of execution of court
override monetary payment, but even things deserving of כרת, kares, which was
not the opinion of our משנה, Mishna, and then it got to
a whole discussion about how to define those two acts occurring at
the same time so that one would override the other. We now
turn to another aspect of that, which is the fact that things
that are deserving of כרת kares also are deserving of lashes, and
isn't there a principle that somebody doesn't get lashes and pay? So
let's take a look. ורמינהו, V'arminhu, I'll ask you on this משנה,
Mishna, אלו הן הלוקין, Elu hen ha-lokin, the following people get lashes.
So let's bracket the fact that it's deserving of כרת, kares, let's
look at the fact that if that the way כרת kares is
prosecuted in the court is by giving, administering lashes.
הבא על אחותו ועל אחות אביו ועל אחות אמו ועל אחות אשתו
ועל אשת אחיו ועל אשת אחי אביו ועל הנדה. Ha-ba al achoto
ve-al achot aviv ve-al achot imo ve-al achot ishto ve-al eshet achiv
ve-al eshet achi aviv ve-al ha-niddah. Okay, so all of these are
איסור כרת issur kares and they would be they would be punished
in the court by lashes. וקיימא לן, Ve-kayma lan, top of ל"ב
Lamed bet עמוד א', Amud aleph, and we have the position דאין
לוקה ומשלם, de-ein lokeh u-meshalem, that you don't get both lashes and
pay. Now the language here of אין לוקה ומשלם ein lokeh u-meshalem
is a different language than admittedly the one that never actually was
said explicitly before, but קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, kim lei bidravah minei,
or like
חייבי מיתות שוגגין chayvei mitot shogegin or so on. This is a
language of that we don't actually administer both punishments. We don't give
you lashes and make you pay. So the easiest answer to this,
question of the גמרא Gemara again is, how could you get lashes?
How could it be if you get lashes for these things, how
could our משנה Mishna say you pay? The easiest answer is that
it's a case where we didn't actually administer the lashes. For example,
there were no witnesses, or I mean, of course if there's no
witnesses why are you paying? Or you weren't given fair warning, you
weren't given התראה. hatra'ah. Okay, which is an answer the גמרא Gemara
will say, and that is the easiest answer. The reason I emphasize
it here is again so you understand that there's a difference, that
the idea of something that's deserving of court execution or כרת, kares,
the sense is that actually that sin overrides the punishment- overrides so
that there's no liability for the other thing, whereas here it's actually
the question of that the court won't administer both punishments. We won't
give you both lashes and make you pay.
But if you get lashes, it gets
you out of כרת, kares, right? Yes. Okay, so how is it
that, so again we'll give an answer that it's a case where
we didn't actually give you the lashes, there was no התראה, hatra'ah,
there was no warning. But let's even assume that our משנה Mishna
is even when we were going to give you the lashes. Okay,
how is it that if you get lashes the משנה Mishna is
telling you that you pay? So אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, so says
עולא, Ulla, לא קשיא. lo kashya. כאן באחותו נערה כאן באחותו בוגרת.
Kan be-achoto na'arah kan be-achoto bogeret. The difference is is that when
do we give you lashes,
when do you pay, when it's the case of נערה, na'arah, the
case in the תורה Torah where there's a קנס. knas. When do
we give you lashes? When it's the case of a בוגרת, bogeret,
a girl that is over twelve and a half and there's no
longer a payment. And since there's no longer a payment of the
קנס, knas, that's why there will be lashes, which basically means, the
גמרא Gemara spells out,
okay, no, the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that here. Anyway, which basically
means that עולא Ulla is of the opinion that if you have
to choose between lashes and payment, we would assume lashes, that's the
more severe one. But עולא Ulla seems to be expressing the idea
that no, that actually you would pay rather than get lashes. It's
true you can't get both. So if you can't get both, which
one are you going to get? So עולא Ulla says you'll pay,
you'll pay the money. So our משנה Mishna that says you pay
the fine? Sure, because even though you're deserving of lashes, you will
pay the fine rather than get the lashes. The משנה Mishna that
says you get lashes, that's in a case where there is no
fine. First of all, it could just be a case of consensual,
that's an easy case that there's no fine. Number two is, it
could also be a case where she's not a נערה, na'arah, so
there's no fine. So basically עולא Ulla is saying, whenever there is
money and lashes, you won't do both, but what you'll do is
the money. And that's why our משנה Mishna could be a case
where they warned you and you're deserving of lashes and nevertheless you'll
pay the
money. Okay? כאן באחותו נערה כאן באחותו בוגרת. Kan be-achoto na'arah kan
be-achoto bogeret. So the גמרא Gemara says, אחותו בוגרת נמי איכא בושת
ופגם. Achoto bogeret nami ika boshet u-pagam. So the גמרא Gemara says,
I don't get it, even if it's a case of a sister
who is not a נערה, na'arah, there's still going to be money.
Why will there be money? Because the idea that the girl has
to be a נערה na'arah is only for the fine of the
fifty שקל. shekel. Okay, but if somebody rapes a woman, whether it's
exactly in the category of נערה na'arah or not. forget the special
fine of the fifty שקל *shekel*, there's other types of payments, like
the basically the thing you have to know and which will be
coming up is that in הלכה Halacha *halacha*, rape is not treated
differently than any act of physical violence. Okay, not treated more stringently,
not treated less stringently either. It's an act of physical violence against
a person. And therefore in the special case of the נערה ne'ara,
*na'arah* that we've been dealing with, the נערה בתולה betulah *na'arah betula*
and so on, there's going to be an extra fine of fifty
כסף *kesef* and an obligation to marry her and so on. But
even if it weren't in that exact case, it would be an
act of rape would be an act of violence and you'd pay
the same thing you pay about physical violence against a person, which
would be the actual embarrassment caused, the בושת boshes, *boshet*, the צער
tza'ar, *tza'ar*, the pain and suffering. Now, you would also pay נזק
nezek, *nezek*, damages. Now how do you assess damages? Okay, so the
way that the, yeah, so you know, and this is going to
sound harsh, but it's true even if somebody breaks another person's arm,
how do you assess damages? So you know in a court nowadays,
you know, you assess like the loss of what do you call
it of like income that the person would have over the course
of his life. Well, that's actually a different computation and that actually
is well actually שבת sheves, *shevet*, although שבת sheves, *shevet* not really
because שבת sheves, *shevet* is actually the loss of income while you're
recuperating. Okay, and so there's שבת *shevet*, there's ריפוי ripuy *rippuy*, which
is also the hospital bills. Okay, but the actual loss of income
over the course of your life is assessed by looking at how
much is this person would this person the only way we can
give a dollar value to a person is you say how much
would this person go as a slave with the arm and how
much are they going to go slave without the arm? Okay, and
that difference is the way we give a dollar value, which obviously
is not really fair because that doesn't really represent you know even
come close to the real dollar value of what you I mean
any dollar value would be absurd but even an attempt to approximate.
Anyway, those are all discussions for בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*, but they're
going to be relevant here. So here what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
calls פגם *pegam*, you know, the sort of the injury to the
person,
the offense, פגם *pegam* is sort of like the offense or the
stigma or something. But anyway, it means how you assess
נזק *nezek*, damages in a case of rape. Because the again, the
sort of the anguish that would be צער tza'ar, *tza'ar*, okay, that
the embarrassment that would be בושת *boshet*. But in the sense of
like what's analog to the loss of the arm would be the
difference between a slave woman who's a virgin and a slave woman
who's not a virgin. Now why should that matter to a person?
Well, matters let's say because they want to marry off their slave
woman to their slave, so you know again as we've been seeing
in כתובות *Ketubot*, virgins are valued more highly. Okay, so that's what
פגם *pegam* is. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says והאיכא בושת
ופגם boshet upgam *v'ha ika boshet u'pegam*, so even if it's not
the special case of the נערה בתולה *na'arah betula*, okay, there still
is the בושת *boshet* and פגם *pegam*, there still are other payments,
so there would no there would not be lashes because you're saying
whatever there's payments, you don't get lashes. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says בשוטה
*b'shotah*. Okay, she's a woman who is not of right mind, she
is like you know she's got some type of a mental illness
which presumably שוטה *shotah* seems to be somebody that doesn't really like
you know, yeah, it's sort of like probably closest to being to
a schizophrenic. Like somebody who doesn't, I don't mean schizophrenic in the
popular imagination of split personality. I mean schizophrenic like somebody who does
not properly interpret like reality, like doesn't properly you know so therefore
and that type of a person isn't embarrassed and isn't you know
and so so that's the person that there wouldn't be payment for.
But isn't בושת ופגם boshet upgam *boshet u'pegam* these things are going
to the daughter then
because if it's to the father... No, but even if they're paid
to the father, it's the you assess in terms of the damage
done to the person, but it's a good point. והאיכא צערה *v'ha
ika tza'arah*? Okay, but even if she's a שוטה *shotah*, she still
has physical pain, you know, and anguish over it. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says במפותה *bimfutah*. So she is a woman that's not
raped. Let's get it out of the rape case. You want to
know how do you get how do you actually get lashes for
a guy who has sex with his sister, stop talking about rape
and then we have to talk about damages. It's still the case
that she's seduced. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says and she's
and she's an adult, so the father's out of the equation and
she's doing everything willingly. So there's of course nothing. It's just two
young adults having consensual... exactly.
השתא דאתית להכי *hasha d'atit
l'hachi*, now that you're saying that, that she's willing, consensual, אפילו תימא
אחותו נערה *afillu tima achoto na'arah*, she could even be a case
of a נערה *na'arah*. Now if it's a נערה *na'arah*, it's not
so obvious because even if she's מפותה *m'futah*, she's willing, still there's
the father and the תורה Torah *Torah* still has payment of to
the נערה *na'arah* even when she does it willingly because the father
wouldn't want her to be doing it and she's not totally under
her own control and her consent is not sufficient. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says fine, but it could be ביתומה ומפותה *bi'ytomah u'mfutah*.
She's an orphan so the father has no say so she's emancipated
even though she's only twelve years old because the father is dead
and she does it willingly. So in a case of consensual sex
where there's no father, either she's a בוגרת *bogeret* or the father
is dead, okay, she's she's her own adult. So that's the case
there would be no... she's just consensual sex, and that's the case
where there would be lashes. So basically עולא Ulla is of the
opinion, you're right, you don't get lashes and pay, but rather than
saying it's a case where we're not administering lashes and that lashes
is the one that overrides, which is the not logical thing to
say, עולא Ulla is saying actually payment would always override, and the
only time you'll get lashes are in cases where there's no payment.
Yes.
Wait, wouldn't you say some of these are the most vulnerable people?
You know, wouldn't you think there would be some kind of That's
a good point.
some kind of more of a more of a punishment?
Yeah, you're right. You know, you're right. It gets to the funny
part that like that 12 is what we consider to be the
age of adulthood, which is like absurd for us, you know. I
mean, if it said she was insane and had no father, you
wouldn't be saying that, right? But there is a case specifically for
the mentally deranged.
Right,
that's true.
They take advantage of them. Yeah, that's true. You know, you're absolutely
correct. Yeah, absolutely
correct. I don't know. I mean, you know, they societally would try
to obviously have אפוטרופוס epitropes and other people to take care of
them, but you're saying what does it mean that there's not like
extra protections in terms of like the penalties. You know, the sad
thing is that this happens even today, you know, in hospitals, in
for the, you know, in psychiatric hospitals or whatever, you know, people
taking advantage of the mentally ill, sexual advantage of them. I mean,
it happens, you know. So, it's but it's a real problem, you
know. Yeah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אלמא קסבר עולא. Alma kasavar Ulla.
Now it spells out what I what's been implicit. You see that
עולא Ulla is of the opinion: כל היכא דאיכא ממונא ומלקות, Kol
heicha de'ika mammon u-malkus, if you have both of those things that
are deserving, payment and lashes, ממונא משלם מלקא לא לקי. mammona mameshalem
malko lo lalki. You
pay money, you don't get lashes, which is counterintuitive. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: מנא ליה לעולא הא? Menalei le-Ulla ha? Where
does he get this idea from? גמר מחובל בחבירו. Gamar mechovel ba-chavero.
He learns it out from the case of actual doing like physical
injury to another person's person. So מחובל בחבירו דאיכא ממונא ומלקות, mechovel
ba-chavero de'ika mammon u-malkus, now that you there's all these payments for
as I just listed to you the various payments of צער, suffering
and embarrassment and the actual damages and so on, there are actually
five whole payments. We also mentioned ריפוי ripuy, and שבת, which is
hospital bills and time and time out of work because you're recuperating.
So there's a lot of payment. However, you also transgress a negative
prohibition. The negative prohibition is you're not allowed to injure somebody else.
It says לא יוסיף להכותו. lo yosif lehakkoto. Do not by what?
פן יוסיף להכותו מכה רבה. pen yosif lehakkoto makka raba. Yes,
but we learn it out as a קל וחומר kal va-chomer if
it applies to בית דין, beis din, certainly it applies to somebody
who has no right to administer lashes to. And therefore and actually
we will find out that there are cases that you actually get
lashes for injuring somebody else. So at least in principle you should.
So you have something that in principle you injure somebody else you
should get lashes for transgressing and you have payment. And what do
we say? You say we make the payments, you don't give the
person lashes. So מחובל בחבירו דאיכא ממונא ומלקות, machovel ba-chavero de'ika mammon
u-malkus, ממונא משלם מלקא לא לקי. mammona mameshalem malko lo lalki.
You pay the money and you don't get the lashes. אף כל
היכא דאיכא ממונא ומלקות, Af kol heicha de'ika mammon u-malkus, so that
would be a paradigm that whenever there's something that logically you should
get both, ממונא משלם מלקא לא לקי, mammona mameshalem malko lo lalki,
you'll pay the money and you won't get lashes. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute. מה לחובל בחבירו... Mah le-chovel ba-chavero... Were those
cases even possible?
No,
those are cases of חיוב מיתה. chiyuv misa. We're just dealing with
cases about מלקות. malkus. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says מה לחובל
בחבירו שכן חייב בחמשה דברים? mah le-chovel ba-chavero she-ken chayav be-chamisha devarim?
One minute. When you injure somebody as I've been saying telling you,
there are five payments. Okay, there's נזק, the damages, צער, suffering, בושת,
embarrassment, שבת, the... ריפוי, the hospital bills, doctor bills, and שבת, the
time out of work because you're recuperating. Five payments. So it's very
weighty. So because it is so weighty, right, that's why the תורה
Torah will want you to therefore pay the money, which is now
it's not which is basically you have to understand that the גמרא
Gemara is not certain which one logically is more weighty. If we
had to judge, which is more weighty, money or lashes? Okay, the
גמרא Gemara is going to deal with both possibilities. So now we're
assuming that a monetary payment is more weighty. So we're saying okay,
I understand that when you have to choose between the two, we're
going to make you pay money. The more we're going to give
you the more weighty payment. Well no, not in specifically in this
case, in general if I had to rank them I'd say paying
money is a more weighty type of a thing than getting lashes.
I don't know why, that's a little ironic, but that's what we're
assuming right now. So it's saying okay, we understand that when you
have to choose between the two we're going to make you pay
money, we're going to give you the more weighty payment, but we'll
do that in this case of חובל בחבירו chovel ba-chavero where the
תורה Torah has already imposed a lot of weighty payments on you,
so it makes sense that what's going to be the more weighty
payment of paying money. Okay, מה לחובל בחבירו שכן חייב בחמשה דברים.
mah le-chovel ba-chavero she-ken chayav be-chamisha devarim. That's assuming that in general
money is more weighty so and that makes that case a special
case. ואי ממונא לקולא, ve-im mammon lekulla, or the opposite, let's say
that paying money is a more lenient thing and for some reason
the תורה Torah is saying that when you have both you do
the more lenient one. Now of course תוספות Tosfos says what? If
we're willing to assume that money is more lenient why would we
say somebody deserving of both gets the more lenient one applied to
him? So תוספות' Tosfos basic answer is well maybe we're doing it
for the sake of the person who's deserving the money, right. So
yes, it's more lenient, but it's not so much about punishing you,
it's about making the, getting the other person, right, you know, compensating
the other person. So if money is considered more lenient, okay, maybe
still that's what you do in a case of חבלה, Chavalah, you
do the more lenient one. Why? שכן
הותרה מכללה בבית דין, Shekein hutra michlala b'veis din, because the idea
that it's a negative prohibition to hit somebody is there's an exception
to that when בית דין Beis Din administers lashes. So this prohibition
of hitting somebody is not categorical. It's not always prohibited. There are
cases when it's allowed. Okay, and therefore what you did was maybe
not such a weighty transgression. Okay, so maybe the גמרא Gemara says,
yes, you're right. This is a case where you're deserving of lashes
and instead you pay money. But either it's because the תורה Torah
is very מחמיר machmir here and wants, and therefore it's giving you
the harsher punishment of paying money, or the opposite, the תורה Torah
is מיקל meikel here and giving you the lighter punishment of paying
money, but because the transgression was not such a categorical transgression, it
wasn't such a weighty, as weighty of a transgression. But maybe other
cases actually, like the case of a guy and his sister, actually
there you would actually get lashes. Okay, so you can't use that
as a paradigm. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Okay, so if you don't want to learn from חבלה בחבירו Chavalah
b'chaveiro because there's things that make it more weighty and things that
make it more lenient, so the גמרא Gemara says, אלא
גמר מעדים זוממים. Ella gamar me'eidim zomemin. How about the case of
false witnesses? Okay, they come and they testify falsely in the court,
they transgress the prohibition about being עדות שקר, eidus sheker, right, לא
תענה ברעך עד שקר, Lo sa'aneh b'rei'acha eid shaker, right, so bearing
false witness. But and that's deserving of lashes. And they also have
the punishment of כאשר זמם. Ka'asher zamam. So if they testified, for
example, somebody owes somebody a hundred dollars falsely, what do they have
to do? They pay the hundred dollars, כאשר זמם. Ka'asher zamam. Well,
what about the lashes they were supposed to get for false testimony?
So you see monetary payment overrides the lashes. Okay, so אלא גמר
מעדים זוממים מאי עדים זוממים דאיכא ממונא ומלקות, Ella gamar me'eidim zomemin,
mai eidim zomemin de'ika mamona u'malkus, money and lashes, money because כאשר
זמם Ka'asher zamam if it was a monetary case, lashes because of
false testimony. So ממונא משלם ומלקא לא לקי, Mamona meshalem u'malka lo
laki, so they pay money and they don't
get lashes. אף כל היכא דאיכא ממונא ומלקות, Af kol heicha de'ika
mamona u'malkus, so any case where it's about money and lashes, ממונא
משלם ומלקא לא לקי, Mamona meshalem u'malka lo laki, they should pay
money and not lashes. Okay, so we have another paradigm, עדים זוממים.
eidim zomemin. The גמרא Gemara says, no, maybe assuming money is a
stricter punishment, there's something that makes עדים זוממים eidim zomemin more strict,
more weighty. מה לעדים זוממים שכן אינם צריכים התראה. Mah l'eidim zomemin
shekein ainan tzrichim hatra'ah. We have other evidence that עדים זוממים eidim
zomemin is more strict, that they don't need warning, right, that they're
going to get their punishment of כאשר זמם Ka'asher zamam even if
nobody said to them right before they testified, hey, be aware, if
you're testifying falsely, you're going to get כאשר זמם. Ka'asher zamam. So
people, so they don't need התראה, hatra'ah, and normally you need התראה.
hatra'ah. We'll discuss that tomorrow, that's going to be tomorrow's סוגיא. sugia.
So that's evidence that we give more weighty punishments by עדים זוממים,
eidim zomemin, and therefore that's why we give money. But other cases
wouldn't be that way, so there's something about עדים זוממים eidim zomemin
that makes it more strict. That's assuming that money, that's assuming that
money is the weightier punishment. ואם ממונא לקולא, V'im mamona l'kula, if
money is the more lighter punishment, so I'll give you another reason
why that's what you do by עדים זוממים eidim zomemin but not
elsewhere. שכן לא עשו מעשה, Shekein lo asu ma'aseh, because what they
did, they only did something verbal and therefore maybe that's not as
weighty of an act as doing something physical. Okay, so therefore that
might be why the תורה Torah goes easy on them and makes
them pay money, but other people they would actually have to get
lashes. All right, so you understand we have two cases where you
did a sin that's deserving of lashes and instead you pay money.
When you injure somebody else and עדים זוממים eidim zomemin in a
monetary case. And the גמרא Gemara says let's use this as a
paradigm that you always will do the money and not the lashes.
And the גמרא Gemara says no. If we're going to assume that
the money is the weightier punishment, there's things about those two cases
that makes them more weighty and therefore they're getting the more weightier
punishment. Either the case that the תורה Torah already gives you five,
five payments shows that it's more weighty, or the fact that you
don't need, you don't need warning shows that it's more weighty. There
are things that make it more weighty and that's why that's an
exception. Or the opposite way, assuming that money is an easier punishment,
there's things that make those more lenient: the fact that sometimes it's
permitted to hit somebody in lashes in a court, the fact that
they're not actually doing an action, they're just doing speech by the
עדים זוממים. eidim zomemin. So therefore you cannot use those as paradigms
because there's things that makes them special. So the גמרא Gemara just
ends this by saying, okay, but how about using both of them
together? The גמרא Gemara says, אלא גמר מתרוייהו, Ella gamar mitravaihu, let's
learn, fine, you can't learn from any one of, each one of
them, but how about the common denominator of the two of them?
מה הצד השוה שבהן Mah hatzad hashaveh shebahen דאיכא ממונא ומלקות, de'ika
mamona u'malkus, the common denominator is that it's lashes and money, ממונא
משלם ומלקא לא לקי, Mamona meshalem u'malka lo laki, and you pay
the money and you don't get the lashes. אף כל היכא דאיכא
ממונא ומלקות, Af kol heicha de'ika mamona u'malkus, so similarly anytime where
you're choosing between money and lashes, ממונא משלם ומלקא לא לקי, Mamona
meshalem u'malka lo laki, you should pay money and not get lashes.
גמרא Gemara says no, מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן יש בהן צד
חמור. Mah l'hatzad hashaveh shebahen shekein yesh bahen tzad chamur. No, the
common denominator is although they have different things that make them weighty,
each one has something special about it that makes it. weighty and
therefore proves that maybe in certain weighty cases you'll pay money but
not in normal cases. ואי ממונא לקולא, V'i mamona l'kulah, or assuming
that money is a lighter punishment, התם שכן יש בהן צד קולא,
Hatam sheken yesh bahen tzad kulla, there's something about both of them
that makes them more especially lenient cases. And therefore because they're special...
both of them have a leniency, that's why the תורה is going
easy and saying paying money. Okay, but there's no way you can
learn from the two of those to apply to all other cases.
By the way, תוספות Tosfos points out that if you can just
sort of abstract and say צד חמור Tzad chamur and צד קולא,
Tzad kulla, then you'll never be able to do a צד השווה,
Tzad hashaveh, because every time you try to do a צד השווה,
Tzad hashaveh, you try to eliminate the distinctive issues, but if you
could always just abstract it and say, 'Yeah, but everything has something
special about it and that's, you know, put it all in... and
that therefore we can exclude all of them,' you'll never be able
to do a צד השווה. Tzad hashaveh. So anyway, תוספות Tosfos works
that out.
Okay, the two cases here that they're playing with is a חובל
בחברו Chovel b'chavero and עדים זוממין. Edim zomemin. Correct.
So
now the גמרא Gemara said, 'Yes, you're right, both of those are
examples where you pay money and you don't get lashes, but nevertheless,
but nevertheless, they... you cannot use that as a basis as a
general rule. So where does עולא Ulla still know that in our
case by a guy sleeping with his sister, it was a case
of rape, that he would actually pay the fine and the monetary
payment and not get the lashes? That's the question we have. Okay,
by the way... okay, so anyway, let's see. אלא עולא תחת גמר,
Ela Ulla Tachas gamar, תחת תחת גמר. Tachas tachas gamar. He has
a גזירה שווה, Gezeirah shavah, תחת תחת. Tachas tachas. כתיב הכא תחת
אשר ענה, Ketiv hacha tachas asher inah,
here it says by the case of rape, he should pay this
money because
he afflicted her, whatever, you know, he raped her, essentially, because he
raped her. וכתיב התם, U'ketiv hatam,
and it says over there, עין תחת עין, Ayin tachas ayin, eye
for an eye. Here the irony is that the verse about eye
for an eye is used as the basis for as the verse
about monetary payment. Okay, מה התם, Ma hatam, so the same way
that has been traditionally interpreted as ממונא משלם מלקא לא לקי, Mamona
m'shalem malka lo laki, as we've been saying, when you do injury
to somebody you pay money you don't get lashes, אף הכא דאיכא
ממונא ומלקות, Af hacha de'ika mamona u'malkus, so anywhere that there's money
and lashes, ממונא משלם מלקא לא לקי, Mamona m'shalem malka lo laki,
you pay money you don't get lashes. And that's how עולא Ulla
learns it from this גזירה שווה. Gezeirah shavah. Now, this גזירה שווה
Gezeirah shavah specifically is applying to our case, the case of rape.
So תוספות Tosfos says that here the גמרא Gemara actually is shifting,
that you know, it's very... we would really... it's bizarre that somebody
should say as a כל התורה כולה Kol hatorah kullah principle, money
will outweigh lashes, money is the more, you know, is the... if
you have to choose between the two you would pay money. And
we really don't see too much evidence of that. So therefore תוספות
Tosfos says it's better to understand that now that we're making a
גזירה שווה Gezeirah shavah specifically about the case of rape, that עולא
Ulla is just saying this הלכה by rape. When it comes to
rape, you're going to pay the money and not get the lashes,
even if it's a case of rape of a sister, you know,
or rape of somebody that you would be deserving of lashes, which
in a way makes a certain amount of sense. Since by injury
you pay money rather than get the lashes, and one of the
logic of that is because you want the person to be compensated
and that's more important than punishing the guy and giving him the
lashes. So in a case of rape as well, even if it's
a rape that also has with it the prohibition of incest and
sister and so on, we would still more say we want the
money to be paid rather than we want the lashes to be
administered. Okay, so תוספות Tosfos says at this stage we're making a
גזירה שווה Gezeirah shavah to the case of rape, עולא Ulla is
taking the position only by rape. By rape, even in a case
of עריות, Arayot, of like sisters and relatives or whatever, it's always
going to be money not lashes. But as a general rule, עולא
Ulla will concede that you do lashes instead of money.
Yes. It seems to me by the way you've just framed it
is you have to be convinced that by paying the money you
are solving two problems simultaneously which the lashes would not solve. You
are effecting the repair damage and you're causing a deterrence to the
perpetrator, because otherwise if the deterrence piece is left undone, there's something
missing. Right.
That's true, but you know, but based on... look, the principle that
you don't get both is a little strange. Like why not get
both? Right? If there's two separate issues that need to be addressed,
right? Like you know, like the O.J. Simpson thing, right? You've got
the criminal prosecution, you've got the civil prosecution. Why can't you do
both? So, and for whatever reason once that's our principle, it doesn't
mean that if we're going to choose one of them we're necessarily
going to achieve both ends. For example, if we choose the lashes,
we're not going to achieve the ends of compensation. So if we
choose the compensation, we won't necessarily achieve the ends of the lashes.
You're just saying why should we have to choose between the two
of them? But I'm telling you, don't assume that when we make
the choice we're assuming that all of our goals are being realized.
You know, it's actually not, we're actually having to choose between our
goals. Yes.
Is this not taking into consideration somebody who's wealthier? Right.
Because his action might
really be irrelevant to them because they know they can just pay.
pay, pay, pay for it, exactly. I mean that goes to דב's
Dov point, which is that if you do the payment and not
the lashes, you've lost the deterrent, right? So I mean it just
really gets to the question of that what's the logic of saying
you don't do both?
Right, maybe you're saying there is no logic, it's גזירת הכתוב. gezerat
hakatuv.
I understand, but I'm just saying we're still trying to understand it.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, but whether even if it's the
other way, it's no logic to say you only get the lashes.
Okay, that might be true in terms of the deterrent and punishing
and so on, but what about the poor guy that's not being
compensated because you've decided all you can do is to do the
lashes?
Right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, by the way, I
mean I guess it's an interesting question, like in all these cases
about murder trials and all those things,
why isn't there always an associated civil suit that goes with them?
I assume murder defendants don't have money.
Aha, aha.
But when they do have money, there will often be, yes, is
a civil suit that comes along with it. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. And a number of the people
who commit murders don't usually have money.
Right, okay, got it.
All right, so I guess just point we're saying it's all
גזירת הכתוב gezerat hakatuv and that's it.
Right, yes. Correct.
Just, that's the way תוספות Tosafot understands it, yes. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, so that's answer number one. Answer, so and again,
the question is our משנה Mishna has that when you did, the
guy did the sin of incest and rape, that he pays the
money. So the first discussion yesterday, last two days was, is a
חייב כרת hayav karet override payment of money the same way a
חייב מיתה hayav mita does, an act that's deserving of כרת, karet,
an act that's deserving of the court punishment? Here, it's not about
just deserving, it's the actual administration of lashes. If we give him
lashes, why shouldn't that override the monetary payments? And עולא's Ulla answer
is because at least in this case, similar to the case of
injury, we are saying that you pay the that payment is what
overrides the giving of the lashes. That's עולא's Ulla answer. Okay, let's
now see. רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו תימא אחותו נערה. Rabbi Yochanan amar
afilu tema achoto ne'ara. No, it could be a classic case of
the sister who's a נערה, which is both deserving of lashes and
money, and nevertheless you're going to pay the money. Why you're going
to pay the money? כאן שהתרו בו כאן שלא התרו בו, kan
she-hitru bo kan she-lo hitru bo, that in one case they gave
warning, the other case they did not give warning, which means that
עולא Ulla says you're right, if you had to choose, you choose
the lashes, but it happens to be a case where we're not
going to administer the lashes because there was no warning. אלמא קסבר
רבי יוחנן, alma kasavar Rabbi Yochanan, you see that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan holds, כל היכא דאיכא ממונא ומלקותא ואתרו ביה מילקא לקי ממונא
לא משלם, kol heicha de-ika mamona u-malkuta ve-atru bei milka larki mamona
lo meshalem, if you have to choose between money and lashes and
you've given warning,
you get lashes, you don't pay money. So again, just so it's
clear to you, קים ליה בדרבה מיניה kim leh bederabba minei means
that when you're dealing with something that's of the חייב מיתה hayav
mita variety or כרת, karet, which is similar for רבי נחוניא בן
הקנה Rabbi Nechunya ben Hakana who says it, then it's even without
any warning. I mean כרת, karet, what do you need התראה hatra'ah
for כרת? karet? כרת karet is just between you and God. But
it means that it's so heavy that it's deserving of the death
penalty or deserving of כרת karet for רבי נחוניא בן הקנה, Rabbi
Nechunya ben Hakana, then that overrides any liability that's occurred at the
same time. This, that's what we dealt with yesterday. That does not
need warning. That's just the weight of the עבירה. aveira. This is
specifically the idea that the court won't administer both punishments. אין אדם
לוקה ומשלם, ein adam lokeh u-meshalem, we're not going to do both
things to you. And therefore רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said if you
didn't give warning, then you can pay the money. But if you
gave warning and you're going to give the lashes, you won't pay
the money. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and עולא Ulla disagree in
the case of rape whether the or the rape of incest, I
should say, normal rape they would agree you pay the money and
not the lashes, that would be like חבלה. chavala. But the case
of a rape of incest, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say you
give lashes if you're able to and עולא Ulla? would say no,
you always pay money even if you're able to give lashes. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מנא ליה לרבי יוחנן הא?
minalei le-Rabbi Yochanan ha? Where does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan know that
as a general rule and including this case, lashes when they're administered
overrule payment?
אמר קרא amar kra because the verse says כדי רשעתו, kdei rish'ato,
and here finally we're getting a פסוק pasuk that tells me this
principle
of only one punishment. It says in a verse about lashes, it
says according to his wickedness you shall basically, you know, give him
the lashes. משום רשעה אחת רשעתו, mishum rish'ah achat rish'ato, because of
his one wickedness. משום רשעה אחת אתה מחייבו, mishum רשעה אחת אתה
מחייבו, you can make him liable for one act of wickedness, ואי
אתה מחייבו משום שתי רשעויות, ve-i atah mechayvo mishum shtei rishayot, but
not because of two acts of wickedness. Of course the irony is
if they occur concurrently, right. The irony is that actually you can
give somebody multiple sets of lashes, like the גמרא in מכות Makkot
has a case of like if you eat an ant you get
five, you're חייב hayav for five different עבירות, aveirot, right? For this
type of an insect and that type of an insect and so
on. So actually you can get for multiple different עבירות aveirot multiple
sets of lashes. But what you can't get is lashes and monetary
payment. Even on the monetary payment is probably coming from a different
perspective than the lashes perspective, right? If you think about it in
terms of let's say the case of sister and rape, the lashes
has to do with sister, the monetary punishment has to do with
rape, and even so you can't do both. So it's a little
ironic you can do multiple sets of lashes, but you... Anyway, I
guess the point is that if they're at an equal level, they
don't really one doesn't win out over the other. משום דמשום אחת
אתה מחייבו ואתה מחייבו משום שתי רשעויות, mishum desh'achas ata mechayvo v'ata
mechayvo mishum shtei rishayuyos, וסמיך ליה, v'samich lei, and then it says
ארבעים יכנו, arba'im yakenu, and then it says give him lashes. So
what it's telling you is, is that if you have to choose,
you're only going to administer one punishment, the more severe one presumably,
and then it tells you give him lashes. So it's telling you
lashes is the more severe punishment over money. And therefore you give
lashes rather than money. So the Gemara says, how about the exceptions?
So the Gemara says like this: והרי חובל בחבירו, v'harei chovel b'chaveiro,
but wait a minute, what how do you deal with the exceptions?
Like doing a physical injury to somebody, דאיכא ממון ומלקות, d'ika mamon
u'malkus, that that's deserving of money and lashes, ממון משלם ומלקא לא
לקי, mamon meshalem u'malka lo laki, and you pay money and you
don't get lashes. וכי תימא הני מילי היכא דלא אתרו ביה, v'chi
teima hani mili heicha d'lo asru bei, let's say you want to
say well maybe not, maybe if they gave the guy warning, maybe
he would just get lashes and not pay money. No. I mean
first of all that like there goes all compensation. אבל אתרו ביה
מלקא לקי ממון לא משלם, aval asru bei malka laki mamon lo
meshalem, but if they gave him warning, maybe you would think that
you give lashes and you don't pay for personal injury. The Gemara
says no, והאמר רב אמי אמר רבי יוחנן, v'ha'amar Rav Ami amar
Rabi Yochanan, Rav Ami says in the name of Rabi Yochanan, הכאה
שאין בה שוה פרוטה לוקה. haka'ah she'ein bah shaveh perutah lokeh. If
he gave him a wounded him, a type of a wound that
is not even is not even the value of a perutah, meaning
so if the payments you actually inflicted a wound so you transgressed
a negative prohibition, but the actual the actually it was so trivial
that there was actually no money to be paid, not for nezek,
not for tza'ar, not for sheves, not for ripuy, nothing. Okay? The
actual doctor's bills came to zero. All right? So if you had
can imagine some case like that, then you would have transgressed the
prohibition without any payment, then we'll give you lashes. Forty lashes?
Forty lashes. For like nothing? Exactly.
I know, it's completely ironic, right? The most trivial thing, then you
get forty lashes. If you do a more serious thing, you cut
off a guy's arm, then you pay monetary payments, no lashes. Okay?
ממון ופחות משוה פרוטה אפילו בושת. mamon u'pachos mishaveh perutah afilu boshes.
Right.
So that means that it's a case where there's not even any
embarrassment, there's I mean Rashi deals with the cases, okay? But some
case where there's absolutely no money to be paid for any of
the five payments. All right? In that case לוקה lokeh you get
lashes. היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי דלא אתרו ביה,
i d'lo asru bei, if there was no warning, אמאי לוקה, amai
lokeh, why would he get lashes? אלא פשיטא דאתרו ביה, ela peshita
d'asru bei, it must be that there was
warning, וטעמא דליכא שוה פרוטה, v'tama d'leika shaveh perutah, and the only
reason you get lashes, it's a special case that it's not even
a perutah's worth of damage. One imagines this would never really happen,
okay, but it's interesting as a as a category of putting out
there that in theory you're deserving of lashes.
You're not allowed to touch somebody else even
affectionately.
הא איכא שוה פרוטה, ha ika shaveh perutah, well it would have
to be described as an act of injury anyway of afflicting injury
anyway, but if there is a perutah's worth, ממון משלם ומלקא לא
לקי, mamon meshalem u'malka lo laki, even if there is warning, it's
clear that once there's a payment to be paid, even if there's
warning, you pay the money, you don't get lashes. So now we've
got the question. You're telling me that the general principle is money
lashes and not money, how do you explain why in a case
of personal injury it's money instead of lashes? So the Gemara says,
I mean now the logic is fine, the logic is because you
want this guy to be compensated, but what's your basis in the
pesukim for saying such a thing? So the Gemara says, כדאמר רבי
אילא, k'd'amar Rabi Ila, like Rabi Ila says, בפירוש ריבתה תורה עדים
זוממים לתשלומין. b'feirush ribesah Torah eidim zomemim l'tashlumin. He's going to say
this in our next case, which is eidim zomemim, that the Torah
explicitly says that eidim zomemim pay and therefore not get lashes, הכא
נמי, hacha nami, here too say the same by injury, בפירוש ריבתה
תורה חובל בחבירו לתשלומין. b'feirush ribesah Torah chovel b'chaveiro l'tashlumin.
The Torah explicitly included the case of injury said explicitly that the
case of injury is one that there's payment and therefore because there's
going to be payment there's no malka, yeah well that's the only
type of payment, and there's not going to be lashes. Okay. So
basically it's saying you're right, it's an exception because the general rule
is lashes not payment, but here the Torah explicitly says that it's
an exception. Now the Gemara is going to say where does the
Torah say that? והיכא איתמר דרבי אילא, v'heicha itmar d'Rabi Ila, what
was the context of Rabi Ila? אהא, aha, מעידין אנו את איש
פלוני שחייב לחבירו מאתים זוז. me'idin anu es ish ploni shechayav l'chaveiro
masayim zuz.
So this is the other challenge, right? The other exception, which is
eidim zomemim. We testify that this guy owes his friend two hundred
zuz. ונמצאו זוממין, v'nimtze'u zomemin, and they were false witnesses. לוקין
ומשלמין, lokin u'meshalmin, so Rabi Meir's position they get lashes and they
pay. So not what we've been saying, they actually do both. Why?
And here is the logic according to Rabi Meir:
שלא השם המביאן
לידי
מכות מביאן לידי תשלומין דברי רבי מאיר.
shelo hashem ham'vi'an lidei makos
m'vi'an
lidei tashlumin divrei Rabi Meir.
Because the thing that they did that's deserving of lashes, what did
they do that's deserving of lashes? The negative prohibition of לא תענה
ברעך עד שקר, lo sa'aneh b'rei'acha ed shaker,
of falsely testifying. So they get lashes for the prohibition of falsely
testifying. Why do they pay? They don't pay because they transgressed the
prohibition of edus shaker. Edus shaker, you know what the punishment is
for edus shaker? Lashes. You know why they pay? Okay, because they're
of a different category, category called עדים זוממים edim zomemim *Edim zomemim*.
Okay, so even if עדים זוממים edim zomemim. *Edim zomemim* is not
a punishment for transgressing the prohibition of עדות שקר *Eidut shaker*. עדות
שקר *Eidut shaker*, the punishment is lashes. עדים זוממים *Edim zomemim* is
the way the court basically, you know, deals with protecting its own,
like, you know, integrity and so on, and therefore it's and I
mean the whole פסוקים *pesukim* say כל ישראל ישמעו וייראו *Kol Yisrael
yishme'u veyira'u*, it's not just because of your the punishment for your
personal עבירה aveira *avera*. And therefore it's a different category, we'll discuss
that more tomorrow. And therefore those two are not in conflict. Lashes
for עדות שקר *Eidut shaker*, two hundred זוז *zuz* for being an
עד זומם *ed zomem*. Okay? Because you could do עדות שקר *Eidut
shaker* without being an עד זומם *ed zomem*. You probably can't be
an עד זומם *ed zomem* without doing עדות שקר *Eidut shaker*, but
you could do עדות שקר *Eidut shaker* without being עדים זוממים *Edim
zomemim*, right? עדים זוממים *Edim zomemim* has to follow particular procedure in
order to make you into an עד זומם *ed zomem*. All right,
so that, remember, that's what רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says. Okay, וחכמים
אומרים כל המשלם אינו לוקה *Vechachamim omrim kol hamashalem eino lokeh*. But
the rabbis say no, you pay, you don't get lashes. Now the
גמרא *Gemara* is going to say, okay, so now we've identified as
we've been saying חובל chovel *chovel* and עדות שקר *Eidut shaker* as
exceptions. Let's see what the basis is in the תורה *Torah* to
say that they're exceptions and I'll take the question. ונימא כל הלוקה
אינו משלם *Venima kol halokeh eino meshalem*, why not say you get
lashes rather than pay? אמר רבי אילא בפירוש ריבתה תורה עדים זוממים
לתשלומין *Amar Rabbi Ila befirush ribta Torah edim zomemim letashlumin*. The Torah
explicitly said that עדים זוממים *edim zomemim* pay, and therefore if they're
paying, they're not going to get lashes. היכן ריבתה תורה *Heichan ribta
Torah*? Where did the Torah include it? מכדי כתיב ועשיתם לו כאשר
זמם לעשות לאחיו *Michdi ketiv ve’asitem lo ka’asher zamam la’asot le’achiv*. Do
to him like he wanted to do to his fellow. Okay, so
that is, you know, that's already the concept of עדים זוממים *edim
zomemim*, like do what he wanted to do. יד ביד למה לי
*Yad beyad lama li*? Why does it again say hand for hand?
דבר הניתן מיד ליד *Davar hanitan miyad leyad*. יד ביד *Yad beyad*
sort of seems like from one hand to the next hand means
like handing over money.
So what was יד ביד *yad beyad*?
It says by עדים זוממים *edim zomemim*, ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם לעשות
לאחיו יד ביד רגל ברגל עין בעין *ve’asitem lo ka’asher zamam la’asot
le’achiv yad beyad regel beregel ayin be’ayin* etc. Okay, so that's right
in the category of עדים זוממים *edim zomemim*. So why does it
have to say hand for hand after it says do what he
wanted to do? Because hand for hand evokes the image of handing
over money. And therefore the תורה *Torah* is telling you by עדים
זוממים *edim zomemim* you're actually going to pay money if it's a
monetary issue. And if you're going to pay money and you can't
do both, so we see עדים זוממים *edim zomemim* is an exception.
The תורה *Torah* is explicitly saying when money has to be paid,
money is going to be paid. And therefore there won't be lashes.
So that's how you know עדים זוממים *edim zomemim* is an exception.
And now let's see how חובל *chovel* is an exception. חובל בחבירו
נמי *Chovel bachaveiro nami*. So how do you know for חובל *chovel*
that that's an exception? Payment rather than lashes. מכדי כתיב *Michdi ketiv*,
let's take a look. It says כאשר עשה כן יעשה לו *ka’asher
asa ken ye’aseh lo*, as was done so should be done to
him, right? And then it says so, so איש כאשר יתן מום
באדם כאשר עשה כן יעשה לו *ish ka’asher yitein mum ba’adam ka’asher
asa ken ye’aseh lo*. If you make a wound in your friend,
as you had done, so shall be done to you. And then
it, right, and then it goes on to say כן יעשה *ken
ye’aseh*, but then it says כן ינתן בו למה לי *ken yinaten
bo lama li*? But it also says so shall be given to
him. Okay, so why does it say you do to him and
given to him? So what does given mean? דבר שיש בו נתינה
*Davar sheyesh bo netina*, something that is given over. ומאי ניהו ממון
*Umai nihu mamon*. And what is it that's money? So therefore the
תורה *Torah* explicitly, explicitly, explicitly through the eyes of חז"ל *Chazal*, okay,
says by עדים זוממים *edim zomemim* and by חובל *chovel* that there
is going to be payment. And since there's going to be payment,
we learn out that it's going to be payment and not lashes.
Of course the funny thing is is that there's also, I mean,
you know, תורה *Torah* explicitly says payment when it says רק שבתו
יתן ורפא ירפא *rak shivto yitein verafo yerape* and so on, but
maybe that would have been in a case where it wasn't actually
חבלה chavala *chovala*, where it actually wasn't bodily injury. But bodily injury,
okay, I mean although that seems to be the case in the
תורה *Torah*, again it's a little funny to go there, but anyway,
but at least for the payment of נזק *nezak*, the תורה *Torah*
here saying that it's explicitly identifying that you pay the money for
נזק *nezak*. And therefore and it's explicitly saying עדים זוממים *edim zomemim*
pay. One minute, does he have a question first? And therefore we
see עדים זוממים *edim zomemim* pay. And therefore רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
*Rabbi Yochanan* says I can hold by my principle that you give
a guy if you have to choose between money and lashes, you
give lashes. Lashes is the more severe. I learned that from the
פסוק *pasuk* of כדי רשעתו *kedei rishato* which is talking about lashes.
You're going to give lashes. That's the more severe. If the guy
raped his sister and they warned him for lashes, he's going to
get lashes and he's not going to pay. Lashes is the more
severe. There are two exceptions: עדים זוממים *edim zomemim* and חובל *chovel*.
And both of those is because we read from hints in the
verse that those are cases where you'll pay money. But those are
the exceptions. The rule is lashes. And עולא Ulla *Ulla* might agree
to the rule, but he would say this case of rape and
incest coming together, that's an also an exception and that's a case
like חובל *chovel* where you would pay rather than giving lashes. Jonathan,
you had a question.
There you go.
In the case of עדים זוממים *edim zomemim*, let's say it was
a case of corporal punishment, right? You think that, you know, certainly
at least in that case you'd give them something physical instead of
explaining יד ביד *yad beyad* as something monetary. Sure, I mean that's
the irony of it.
Well, you do, but there are cases where you pay money. I
mean רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* would say you can give two sets
of lashes: one lashes for עדים זוממין *Edim Zomemin* and one lashes
for עד שקר *Ed Sheker*. רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* sort of sees
them as two separate cases.
Yeah, but how was it say to עדים זוממין *Edim Zomemin*, if
I was testifying this guy would give מלקות *Malkos*, deserves מלקות *Malkos*,
then according to what we were just saying a second ago to
יד תחת tachat יד *Yad Tachat Yad*, I don't pay money.
That's יד תחת tachat יד *Yad Tachat Yad* is for one scenario
of it, not every scenario of it. Okay, there's a lot of
things... sure, of course, yeah, yeah, these are cases of money. Okay,
so גמרא *Gemara* says like this. Now interestingly, right the גמרא *Gemara*
it wants to it's gonna ask why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi
Yochanan* doesn't say like עולא Ulla *Ulla*, it's not gonna say the
verse, why doesn't עולא Ulla *Ulla* say like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
*Rabbi Yochanan* even though רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* is the
more logical position. But okay, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan מאי טעמא לא
אמר כעולא *Rabbi Yochanan mai taama lo amar ke'Ulla*? Why does רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* not say like עולא Ulla *Ulla* that
at least let's say in the case of rape and incest coming
together that you actually pay the money rather than get the lashes.
אם כן בטלת ערות אחותו לא תגלה *Im ken bataltah ervat achoto
lo tegaleh*. No, I can't say that you're going to pay money
and not get lashes in that case. It's undermining the negative prohibition
of incest, right? Because you're basically saying that the guy's not gonna
have the lashes as a deterrent and as an appropriate punishment. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says... okay, so therefore basically, which is interesting because
what it really does is it reflects, you know sometimes you read
גמרא *Gemara* and you get the sense like okay, so they're just
having technical disagreements, you read the פסוק *pasuk* this way, you read
the פסוק *pasuk* that way. But what's behind the technical disagreements? Why
is עולא Ulla? *Ulla* choosing to make this גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*
of תחת tachat *tachat* and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* not?
And the גמרא *Gemara* really here says because רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
basically feels that lashes are the more important thing. You have a
weighty sin, you gotta give the weighty punishment, you gotta give the
punishment of lashes. It's not appropriate to give a lighter punishment. So
that general like philosophy about what would it do to the weight
of the prohibition if we were to say money rather than lashes
is ultimately what informs how he's going to read the verse. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says top of ל"ג עמוד א' *lamed gimmel amud
aleph* that we'll get a little ahead, חובל בחברו נמי Chovel bachavero
nami *chovel bechavero nami*, so if that's true that you're so concerned
about the deterrent aspect or the proper weighty punishment aspect, it doesn't
have to be deterrent, deterrent is I think more of a contemporary
way of thinking about it. Right here it would just be such
a big sin, it deserves the proper punishment. So if that's why
you never want to say money and you always want to say
lashes, so אם כן בטלת לא יוסיף פן יוסיף *im ken bataltah
lo yosif pen yosif*.
So you are nullifying the case of don't,
lest you give him an extra lashes which is the basis for
the prohibition of injuring somebody else. עדים זוממין נמי *Edim zomemin nami*
and false witnesses as well. If you say pay money, you're undermining
the weight of the prohibition. אם כן בטלת והיה אם בן הכות
הרשע *im ken bataltah vehayah im bin hakot harasha*. It will be
if a person is deserving of lashes. So basically...
I missed the question, what's חובל בחברו *chovel bechavero*?
The question is you say you want to choose, you're insistent, you
want to say that by the case of rape and incest you're
going to give lashes, not pay money, because to pay money would
undermine the weight of the prohibition of incest. So the גמרא *Gemara*
is saying well what about the two exceptions where you pay money
and don't get lashes: עדים זוממין *edim zomemin* and חבלה *chavala*? If
you're going to say pay money, why isn't that undermining the weight
of the prohibitions there? And if that's not undermining the weight of
the prohibitions there, it shouldn't undermine the weight of the prohibition here.
Now of course the answer could be you're right, I am bothered
by those cases but I'd rather not expand them, I'd rather... right.
Okay, but the גמרא *Gemara* wants to just ask what logic do
you have if you feel paying money undermines the weight of the
prohibition, how do you explain the logic of those two exceptions? So
let's take a look what the גמרא *Gemara* says. אלא עדים זוממין
אפשר לקיומה בבן גרושה ובבן חלוצה beven gerusha ubeven chalutza. *Ella edim
zomemin efshar lekiyuma beven gerusha uven chalutza*. The weight of the prohibition
of עדים זוממין *edim zomemin* is not undermined because there are times
you will give lashes. What will be a time you'll give lashes
for the prohibition of false testimony? When it's impossible to impose on
the witnesses what they were testifying about somebody else. How would it
be impossible? If they testified that a certain כהן *kohen* was a
בן גרושה *ben gerusha*, right was the son of a divorcee and
a חלוצה *chalutza*, and these people are ישראל *Yisrael*, or even if
they're כהנים *kohanim*, how do you make a כהן *kohen* into a
בן גרושה *ben gerusha*? Okay so it's true, anyway so there's no
way you can do כאשר זמם *ka'asher zamam*.
Oh I understand that, why can't...
I'm a ישראל *Yisrael*, I now testified that a כהן *kohen* is
a חלל *chalal*. Okay, I'm a false witness, I'm an עד זומם
*ed zomem*. What are you going to do to me? You want
to make me a חלל *chalal*? Fine, what does making me a
חלל *chalal* do? Makes me a non-כהן *kohen*, I'm already not a
כהן *kohen*, there's nothing you can do.
Oh, because of the nature of the... I see.
So when it's not about money and lashes, which you could always
do to somebody else, impose money and impose lashes, status things can't
apply. So therefore in that case you can't do כאשר זמם *ka'asher
zamam*. And when you can't do כאשר זמם *ka'asher zamam*, then you
know what you do? You give me lashes for being transgressing the
prohibition of bearing false witness. So there will be a case where
I will get lashes for the prohibition of being a false witness.
So the fact that I pay money and do כאשר זמם *ka'asher
zamam* doesn't undermine the weight of the prohibition because that is already...
Always there on the background waiting to get lashes if you don't
do the other stuff. And that's considered at least in theory enough
to maintain the weight of that prohibition. So that אפשר לקיומיה you
can fulfill the lashes for the transgression בבן גרושה ובבן חלוצה. חובל
בחברו נמי in a case where of injury, you'll say oh, you'll
never get lashes for this prohibition, so it's undermining the weight. No!
איכא לקיומיה Ika lekiyumay כגון שהכהו הכאה שאין בה שווה פרוטה. kegon
shehikahu hakaa sheein ba shaveh pruta. In that bizarre case where it's
an injury that has less than a פרוטה's pruta worth of damage,
so you would get lashes. So at least in theory these remain
prohibitions that can get lashes for, even that though that'll only occur
once in a million years, but they remain in theory prohibitions you
can get lashes for and that's okay. So if you're okay with
the case of injury and the case of עדים זוממים that the
that paying money doesn't undermine the weight of the עבירה aveira because
the עבירה at least in theory is still deserving of lashes and
there might be one rare case where it gets it. So here
too, here's even a bigger category. The גמרא says אחותו נמי achoto
nami the case of sex with of a brother and a sister.
Actually in most cases if it's consensual, there actually will be cases
you know most cases will be lashes and not money. So in
that case איכא לקיומיה ika lekiyumay באחותו בוגרת bachoto bogeret if the
sister is an adult and it's consensual then there will be lashes
and not money. Okay which is basically right it's a very strong
point. רבי יוחנן is saying look I'd rather get lashes than money.
Giving money undermines the weight of the prohibition. The גמרא says well
what about the exceptions? The exceptions about חבלה and עדים זוממים. Now
as Michael responded as I would say say fine those are exceptions
but I don't want to extend it beyond those cases. But the
גמרא is saying no, you have to deal with the exceptions and
if in those cases we say the prohibition isn't undermined because sometimes
you still will get lashes, in this case actually the majority of
the time with cases of incest there'll be lashes. So the fact
that in some cases it'll also be a case of rape it
will be a case of rape and there'll be money instead of
lashes, you can't say oh it's going to undermine the weight of
the prohibition. The prohibition of incest is weighty enough and most of
the time actually there will be lashes. So bottom line רבי יוחנן
why not say like עולא? Ulla Why not have him pay money
rather than have him get lashes? Again why we're presupposing that עולא's
is the more logical position and רבי יוחנן has to defend himself,
I don't know, maybe again because even though lashes is more weighty
maybe we want the person to be compensated. So רבי יוחנן why
are you not saying like עולא to pay the money? So the
גמרא says and with this we'll end: אמר
לך רבי יוחנן Amar lach Rabbi Yochanan רבי יוחנן will say to
you האי תחת אשר עינה hai tachat asher ina
because עולא got it from a verse תחת tachat right he used
the תחת tachat by rape connect to the תחת of עין תחת
עין. ayin tachat ayin. So no I use it for something else.
מיבעי ליה לכדאביי Mibaya lei lachad’Abaye so now we're getting into a
technical argument rather than a principled argument.
מיבעי ליה לכדאביי דאמר אביי אמר קרא תחת אשר עינה Mibaya lei
lachad’Abaye deamar Abaye amar kra tachat asher ina that you pay for
that for the rape that's the fifty shekel האי תחת אשר עינה
hai tachat asher ina the fact that it says you're paying the
fifty shekel
for the rape מכלל דאיכא בושת ופגם. michlal deika boshet upgam. It
means that there are other payments also that have to be made.
So in addition to the fifty okay but I understand but that's
a דרשה drasha that this is what's being paid for the for
the fact that it's specifically this act of rape but other things
which are normal to any injury like בושת ופגם embarrassment and loss
of you know loss of value and so on and the cost
of the injury itself that those payments are still going to be
made. The fifty shekel does not override the other normal payments that
you make for for cases of injury. Not of
injury of personal what do you call that? Not I guess injury
but personal injury yes. Injury sounds like it happened accidentally but anyway
what do you call inflicting physical damage on somebody so a word
for that in English? חובל is the Hebrew word. Batter? Battery I
guess right. Assault and battery. Anyway so the גמרא says like this
ועולא נפקא ליה veUlla nafka lei oh so that's where he so
I need תחת to tell me something else ועולא נפקא ליה מדרבא
veUlla nafka lei mideRava now עולא since he uses תחת to say
you pay money he learns this idea that there are other payments
from the verse that רבא Rava learns it from. דאמר רבא אמר
קרא Deamar Rava amar kra the verse says ונתן האיש השוכב עמה
לאבי הנערה חמישים כסף venatan haish hashochev ima laavi hanaara chamishim kasef
the man who sleeps with her should pay to the father fifty
silver units of silver. הנאה שכיבה חמישים Hanaat shechiva chamishim for the
pleasure of sex which is again interesting here's a case of rape
and we're talking about the pleasure of sex for the pleasure of
sex for the act of sex he's paying the fifty מכלל דאיכא
בושת ופגם michlal deika boshet upgam there are other payments that also
have to be made בושת ופגם but for the act of sex
is fifty but in the end of the day why are we
saying that רבי יוחנן doesn't read like עולא? Because for technical reason
he uses the verse to tell me something else. So the general
rule is money and lashes you give lashes you don't pay. So
the general rule is money and lashes; you give lashes, you don't
pay money. But עולא says that at least in the case where
it's about rape and incest coming together, we will pay the money
for the rape rather than doing the lashes for the incest. And
רבי יוחנן says no, we will do the lashes for the incest.
Okay, yeah? If a
פתח petach is worth 50, then why do we say the difference
between the כתובה ketubah and a בתולה and an אלמנה almanah is
100? The only difference...